<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rant | Rainer writes stuff]]></title>
  <link href="http://rdrey.github.io/blog/categories/rant/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rdrey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-28T19:54:30+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://rdrey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rainer Dreyer]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Namibian Guide to SA Universities]]></title>
    <link href="http://rdrey.github.io/blog/2013/09/28/namibian-guide-to-sa-universities/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-28T12:39:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://rdrey.github.io/blog/2013/09/28/namibian-guide-to-sa-universities</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You want to go to university? You&rsquo;re considering South African universities?
Sweet, read on.</p>

<p>This is the kind of guide I couldn&rsquo;t find when I was a Grade 11 student at Namib
High School. Since this is all based on my individual experience &ndash; and I was a
1st year student at UCT in 2007 &ndash; your mileage may vary.</p>

<p>This guide will help you
make some decisions if you&rsquo;re in Grade 10 &amp; 11. <!-- more --> If you&rsquo;re in Grade 12, you
might be too late to change your school subject choices and improve your marks.</p>

<p>The first step is obviously deciding what you want to study. I personally don&rsquo;t
think you can get this 100% right while you&rsquo;re in high school, so instead you
should make some good decisions that will afford you the maximum flexibility
later:</p>

<h3>What do you enjoy learning the most in high school?</h3>

<p>This is the <strong>only reliable data point</strong> you have in high school. You already know
that you love art / music / mathematics / biology / chemistry / sports /
computers / social stuff.
Chances are that you get good marks in your favourite subject. (Or at least
high marks compared to your other subjects.)</p>

<p>At university you will compete with class mates who love what they do. If you
want to be an above-average student, you should really love what you do, too.</p>

<blockquote><p>But I hate school!</p></blockquote>

<p>What do you hate about school? Do you hate your school life, or do you hate
the process of learning? If you hate to learn, this guide cannot help you. If
you hate your school life, you&rsquo;ll find that a lot of things are better at
university than in your (small town) Namibian life.</p>

<h3>What university / faculty should you apply to?</h3>

<p>Pick one or two faculties from SA&rsquo;s top universities that offer the most interesting
degrees in your opinion. You&rsquo;ll want to apply at two to three universities to make sure
you get accepted somewhere. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rankings_of_universities_in_South_Africa">(UCT, Wits &amp; Stellies are your best options for most subjects.)</a></p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;re at a university it is quite <strong>easy to change</strong> your courses within a
faculty, but a lot more work to change faculties. Luckily we can use your
favourite school subjects to get you into one of the right faculties
fairly easily.</p>

<p>Look at the list below and try to narrow down your choices to one or two faculties.
(I&rsquo;ve taken UCT&rsquo;s faculties as an example and annotated each one with what you
should be good at.)</p>

<ul>
<li>Commerce &ndash; accounting, mathematics, social stuff, public speaking</li>
<li>Engineering &amp; the Built Environment (EBE) &ndash; mathematics, physics, chemistry</li>
<li>Health Sciences &ndash; biology, chemistry, social stuff, even sports science</li>
<li>Humanities &ndash; art, music, history, literature, languages, social stuff</li>
<li>Law &ndash; social stuff, languages (a lot of reading), public speaking</li>
<li>Science &ndash; mathematics, physics, chemistry, biology, computer studies</li>
</ul>


<p>Each one of these faculties has exceptions of course. (Civil Engineering can be a
fairly &lsquo;social science&rsquo; in EBE.) And most of the things in <em>my list</em> aren&rsquo;t hard
<em>requirements</em> &ndash; UCT will allow you to do Accounting even if you didn&rsquo;t do it in
school.</p>

<blockquote><p>But universities don&rsquo;t offer what I want!</p></blockquote>

<p>Do you want to be a restaurant manager / real estate broker / hairdresser or
professional sports(wo)man? You don&rsquo;t need to go to university, you should find
vocational training. (But you might want to get a university education later to
accelerate your career.)
You can stop reading this now.</p>

<h3>What are your entrance requirements?</h3>

<p>You will have to figure this out yourself. It will involve reading a lot of
documents on university websites and adding up points to see whether you would
currently meet a university&rsquo;s bar.</p>

<blockquote><p>My teacher says I need <code>x</code> points!</p></blockquote>

<p>Don&rsquo;t listen to your teacher! Go read multiple university websites yourself and
take this advice:</p>

<p>Try to get accepted by your favourite faculty. Don&rsquo;t worry about the degree /
courses yet, <strong>just get in!</strong></p>

<p>If you aim for the &ldquo;minimum requirements&rdquo; for a degree you are <em>very unlikely</em> to
get accepted. Your application will be one of thousands in the &ldquo;maybe&rdquo; bucket and no
one will read it carefully. Whether you were a class captain, debating &amp; soccer
star doesn&rsquo;t matter at this point.</p>

<p>You need to aim for marks higher than the &ldquo;PROBABLE/LIKELY OFFER LEVEL&rdquo;. You really
want to aim for two degrees offered by the same faculty and meet the entrance
requirements for the harder one of the two, which you should put down as your
first choice. (Even if you would rather study your second choice. Crazy, I know.)</p>

<p>If you get accepted for your first choice, great. (Don&rsquo;t stress about courses,
yet. During Orientation week you will learn that you can actually register for
any degree in your faculty, if you were accepted for a &ldquo;hard&rdquo; one.)</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t get accepted by your first choice &ndash; even though your marks were
good enough to put you in the &ldquo;LIKELY OFFER&rdquo; bucket &ndash; your odds of getting
accepted for your second choice just got much higher than everyone else&rsquo;s in
your second choice&rsquo;s &ldquo;LIKELY OFFER&rdquo; bucket.</p>

<p>If your marks don&rsquo;t put you in the &ldquo;LIKELY OFFER&rdquo; bucket for either one of your
choices, good luck &ndash; you&rsquo;ll need it. Your application is now one of many in a
lottery system.</p>

<h3>Study the right school subjects (and more)</h3>

<p>OK, we&rsquo;ve established the marks you need to try to get in the last step.</p>

<blockquote><p>Do. Or do not. There is no try. &ndash; <strong>Yoda</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>Ummm&hellip; I meant to say that we now know the marks you <em>will</em> get. What else
do you need to do in the preparation stage? Quite a lot, actually.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Read your future faculties' handbooks</p>

<p>I managed to do a non-Science major (Economics) in my Bachelor of Science
(Computer Science with Specialization in Game Design). I
also took intro courses for Portuguese, Politics and Astronomy. If you haven&rsquo;t
read your handbook and rules for your degree, you&rsquo;ll never understand the many
options you have at university.</p></li>
<li><p>Follow up with universities a lot</p>

<p>This might be less important now that UCT does Online Applications, but I
only heard that I was accepted 4 days before Orientation Week. I heard back
from my second and third choice universities months before that. Remind the
universities that snail mail to Namibia is slow and that you&rsquo;d like your
correspondence via email, if possible.</p></li>
<li><p>Sort out your finances</p>

<p>Ask your teachers about scholarships and bursary opportunities. I got very
lucky and had Namib High recommend me for a scholarship that paid my tuition
fees for all 5 years of my two degrees.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;re at university it is easier to get bursaries and reduced fees for
academic excellence in second year. Many of my friends had / have student
loans, which also become cheaper if your marks are excellent.</p>

<p>Maximize your chance of getting a bursary by studying one of the following &ndash;
Actuarial Science, Accounting, Petro-Chemical Engineering &ndash;
but be aware that these bursaries will often lock you into a degree and have
multi-year work contracts attached.</p></li>
<li><p>Get a study permit &amp; South African university exemption</p></li>
<li><p>Get high marks!</p>

<p>You might have to study some extra stuff to succeed at universities in South
Africa. We Namibians have a hard time in Mathematics1 at UCT, for example,
because South Africans learn more trigonometry equations. Be aware that your
school might not be preparing you as well as your teachers think.</p></li>
<li><p>Research everything</p>

<p>Search for Communities in your chosen field and follow some of the people
you discover on twitter / Google+. Ask them what books you should read if
you&rsquo;re interested in <code>x</code>. Here are my communities:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news">Hacker News</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/science/">Reddit: Science</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/technology/">Reddit: Technology</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/compsci/">Reddit: CompSci</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.wired.co.uk/">Wired Magazine</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>That&rsquo;s all for now. Good luck with your preparation for university life. Feel
free to contact me if you want to talk about a career in programming. Leave a
comment if you have questions or disagree with my advice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
